welcome to True Health Tuesdays today
we're going to talk about sunshine and
the flu and we seem to be coming out of
the flu season but it's worthwhile
talking about because as we are getting
longer and longer days it's going to be
more important for us to get outside and
take advantage of that sun and even more
importantly as we get into fall and
finally into winter again so it's the
cycle that keeps going and for those who
may have forgotten we didn't have that
great of a flu season this year what I
mean by that was that there was quite a
bit of flu and especially in California
where I and growing up and living here
but for those of you around the country
and even around the world there was some
interesting aspects that we're going to
talk about here with sunshine and the
flu and some studies that have come out
looking at this issue and of course when
we talk about the flu I like to talk
about the Swiss Cheese model no not
specifically eating swiss cheese but
talking about basically this idea that
it takes multiple layers to prevent
something from happening so when we're
in the operating room and we try to
prevent infections from happening we
make sure that the Physicians and the
nurses are scrubbed in they're wearing
sterile gowns they're using sterilized
equipment that they're wearing masks
that we have the air in the room under
positive pressure and a number of things
we want to keep the temperature and the
humidity so all of these are employed to
reduce the incidence of infections and
so when we talk about one or two
different things here in terms of the
influenza remember that we don't mean to
say that the other things that have been
shown to decrease the the influenza
virus are not useful so we mean by that
as flu shots hand hygiene uh
quarantining isolation ventilation these
are all things that are important in
terms of preventing the flu or indeed
other illnesses that are still making
the ways around including covid-19 flu
medicluenza virus the common cold etc
etc so this was a paper that was
published back in 2021 so not too long
ago so what they did here was they
looked at sunlight and protection
against influenza and the key here is
that they were looking at the amount of
sunshine at a specific area over a
number of years and see whether or not
it correlated with influenza risk they
say here that given that sunlight levels
in a geographic area for a particular
week vary randomly over the years this
provides us with a robust estimate so
they looked at a number of years all the
way from 2018 so this is all before the
pandemic and they mapped it out based on
the calendar we week of the year so here
is New Year's as you can see here most
of the flu or influenza-like illnesses
are in that first part of the Year well
there was actually a gear where the flu
came much earlier and that was in 2009
and that year we had an antigenic
shift instead of an antideogenic drift
and that was because this was a
completely different arrangement of the
proteins on the surface of the influenza
virus in fact it was very similar to the
knights the 2009 it was an H1 type of
influenza as you can see at the 2009 flu
season was substantially more severe
than any other season in our sample in
addition there was substantially less
sunlight that year than in the average
Year and much more variability in those
deviations these deviations facilitate
estimation hence 2009 is a clear and
substantial negative relationship
emerges between relative differences in
sunlight and differences in the flu
level so let's take a look and see what
they found when they correlated this and
you can see here that these red dots are
data points from 2009 but for the most
part what you see here is that when you
look at sunlight level in terms of the
mean difference and here's zero which is
sort of starting off at Baseline that as
the amount of log difference of sunlight
goes down the difference in influenza
goes up and conversely as the amount of
sunlight goes up the amount of influenza
goes down and of course this is looking
at a large sample in a national sample
as you can see these other years are
mixed in here again these red this red
area here is a lot of variability that
they saw in 2009 and if we look at the
state of New York which is going to be
obviously a smaller sample size and it's
going to be less variable
here we're looking at County month
deviations for the flu and sunlight in
September and October and we can see
again that when we look here at zero
that as the mean sunlight level goes up
we start to see a general increase in
the sunlight level we see a decrease in
the flu index and when we go below zero
it starts to go up and we actually have
increased levels in the flu so this
caused them to speculate therefore apart
from its methodological contributions
this study reinforces the long-held
assertion that vitamin D protects
against acute upper respiratory
infections we can secure vitamin D
through supplements or through a walk
Outdoors particularly on a day when the
sun shines brightly when most walk herb
protection provides benefit to all
so I would say that it's an interesting
conclusion but that the the notion that
sunlight only provides vitamin D as the
only benefit I think is actually quite
short-sighted here is a study that was
also published in 2009 actually
ironically the same year that we had
that epidemic there of influenza and
they're looking back on a pandemic year
of 1918 1919 and so they're looking at
again vitamin D the possible roles of
solar ultraviolet B radiation and
vitamin D in reducing case fatality
rates in the pandemic during the United
States okay so let's take a look and see
what they did they looked at
specifically different spots in the
United States and they looked at the
number of influenza cases the number of
pneumonia cases the number of influenza
case fatality rates and the number of
pneumonia complications and what they
did was they looked at the amount of
ultraviolet B dose that someone would
get in July so these numbers ostensibly
would be high if you are closer to the
Equator and then latitude would be low
if you are closer to the Equator
remember now that on the globe here's
the equator and here would have a low
latitude here would be a 90 latitude so
we would expect that these two things
here would be inversely proportional to
each other and in fact that is exactly
what we're seeing so latitude here is
the highest and we have the lowest
amount of ultraviolet B radiation here
in San Antonio Texas we have the lowest
latitude and some of the highest levels
of UVB dosing so what did they find when
they looked at the case fatality rates
for instance they found that
the r which is the correlation constant
or r squared here we notice here that
there is a negative correlation between
case fatality rate and the amount of
ultraviolet B radiation which means more
ultraviolet B radiation according to
this or more sunlight is going to drop
your case fatality rate also notice here
that there was a correlation a positive
correlation between case fatality rate
and latitude and notice that both of
these were statistically significant now
what about pneumonia as a complication
of influenza exactly the same thing
ultraviolet B radiation negatively
correlated and that was statistically
significant and it was positively
correlated with latitude and that also
was statistically significant but is it
really ultraviolet B radiation and
vitamin D well this was a study that was
published out of the University of
Edinburgh that looked at ultraviolet a
radiation which is different than b
radiation obviously and covid-19 deaths
in the United States with replication
studies in England and in Italy what
they did was they eliminated all of the
areas of the United States in the winter
time that got enough vitamin D and only
looked at those areas that could not get
enough vitamin D what they found was as
the amount of ultraviolet a radiation or
just basically sunlight as it increased
in dose there was a reduction in the
covid-19 deaths per million same thing
happened here in England as the amount
of radiation from the sun went up there
was a reduction in the case fatality
rate this would have been independent of
vitamin D because this was areas that
you could not have gotten enough vitamin
D at this time of the year and by the
way this was corrected for population
density case proportion Transportation
age ethnicity and comorbidities again
same thing in Italy a reduction in
covid-19 deaths per million when the
amount of radiation went up so it caused
the authors of this study to say in
conclusion this study is observational
and therefore any causal interpretation
needs to be taken with caution however
if the relationship identified proves to
be causal it suggests that optimizing
sun exposure may be a possible Public
Health intervention given that the
effect appears independence of a vitamin
D pathway it suggests new possible
covid-19 therapies and we've talked
about this before is getting out in the
sun even if you're covered the
beneficial effects of the sun is what we
call infrared and that portion is able
to penetrate through linen it's able to
penetrate through cloth it's able to do
what it needs to do and I believe cause
and improvements in health I'm also
recommending this for our long coveted
patients because I believe that in Long
covid the mitochondria have been damaged
by the virus and in order for the
metabolism to improve in order for
energy levels to improve we need to
recycle those mitochondria and protect
them with melatonin and one of the ways
of doing that is good sun exposure but
there are a couple of reasons why people
are not getting sun exposure enough
number one is we spend about 93 percent
of our awaking hours or life inside and
that's got to change we need to make an
effort to get outside even if it's in
the shade getting outside allows us the
ability to get good infrared radiation
notice here that these these kids here
on the orthopedic Wards are still
underneath the canopy so they're not
getting direct sun but they're getting a
lot of near-infrared which basically is
being reflected off of the nice Greenery
so it's very important second reason is
the lights that we have inside our homes
are LED and they do not give off
radiation in the infrared Spectrum so
that's another reason to get outside and
then finally number three the windows on
our modern homes block out in their
infrared radiation so putting all of
these together you can see why very
clearly the amount of near infrared
radiation has gone down a considerable
amount and what we need to do is to get
outside to get our fill of near-infrared
radiation so that when we do it we'll be
pushing more towards this side of the
graph rather than this side of the graph
and that would be one more slice in our
swiss cheese model to help us be
protected against viral antigens until
next time thanks for joining us at true
Health Tuesdays